Sooyong Lee | PhD

Educational Psychology, The University of Texas at Austin

 \square +1 736 865 0618 • \square sooyongl09@gmail.com • \square sooyongl/

Professional Summary

I am a psychometrician with expertise in applying modern statistical theories and techniques. My research interests are in the development and application of statistical models such as such as structural equation modeling (SEM), multilevel modeling (MLM), and item response theory (IRT). Recently, I have focused on Bayesian estimation to model the relationships among variables.

Education

The University of Texas at Austin

Austin, Texas

2017-Present

Ph.D.

O Major in Quantitative Methods

Seoul, Republic of Korea

Korea University M.A.

2014-2017

O Major in Educational Statistics and Measurement

Research experience

CGS PhD Career Pathways project

Graduate Research Assistant

2018/9-2019/5

 Data analysis for surveys to collect data on the career pathways of past and present STEM and humanities PhD students.

President's Award for Global Learning (PAGL)

President's Award for Global Learning (PAGL)

Graduate Research Assistant

2019/1-2019/8

O Designing a culturally appropriate mobile application to increase mental health literacy and self-care habits among South Korean young adults

COE Full-Time Tenured and Tenure-Track Faculty Graduate Research Assistant 2019/9-2019/12

O Data analysis for surveys of graduate programs of education at the University of Texas at Austin

MAAT package development project

Graduate Research Assistant

Northwest Evaluation Association (NWEA)

2019/9-2020/5

O Development of MAAT package for Computerized Adaptive Testing for Northwest Evaluation Association (NWEA)

FLPS project

Graduate Research Assistant

 $IES\ grant$ \odot Development of FLPS package for Fully-latent Principal Stratification

Embedded Standard Setting (ESS)

Intern

Creative Measurement Solutions LLC

2020/6-2020/8

2021/9-Present

O Internship for developing Shiny app for Embeded Standard Setting

Embedded Standard Setting (ESS)

Creative Measurement Solutions LLC

Intern

2021/6-2020/8

Internship for developing ESS package for Embedde Standard Setting

Teaching experience

Structural Equation Modeling

Professor Tiffany Whittaker

Teaching Assistant 2020/1-2020/5

Structural Equation Modeling

Professor Tiffany Whittaker

Teaching Assistant 2021/1-2021/5

Publications

2021

Cory L. Cobb, Charles R. Martínez, Jr., Sooyong Lee, Tae Kyoung Lee, & Elma I. Lorenzo-Blanco, (2021). Acculturation trajectories differ by youth age at arrival and time in residency among Latino immigrant families in a US emerging immigrant context. International Journal of Intercultural Relations, 81, 79-93.

2022

- Sooyong Lee & Tiffany A. Whittaker, (2022). Comparison of Three Approaches to Class Enumeration in Growth Mixture Modeling when Time Structures are Variant Across Latent Classes. Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal, 29, 23-35.
- Seung Choi, Sangdon Lim, Luping Niu, Sooyong Lee, Christina M. Schneider, Jay Lee, & Garron J. (2022). maat: An R Package for Multiple Administrations Adaptive Testing. Applied Psychological Measurement, 46-1, 73-74.
- Sooyong Lee, Suhwa Han, & Seung W. Choi (2022). DIF Detection With Zero-Inflation Under the Factor Mixture Modeling Framework. Educational and Psychological Measurement, 82-4, 678-704.
- Sooyong Lee & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2022). Parallel Process Latent Growth Modeling with Multivariate Confounders/Suppressors. Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal.
- Sooyong Lee, Kahyun Lee, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2022). Application of Associative Discrete-Time Survival Analysis Using Latent Transition Specification. Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal.,

2023

- Sooyong Lee, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2023). Fully-Latent Principal Stratification. The Annual Meeting of the Psychometric Society (in print)
- Sooyong Lee, Suhwa Han, & Seung Choi (2023). Bayesian MIMIC for DIF Detection under Violation of Equal Variance Assumption. Educational and Psychological Measurement (in review)
- Tiffany A. Whittaker, Laura Stapleton & Sooyong Lee (2023). A Tutorial for Obtaining Item Response Theory Results from Structural Equation Modeling in Mplus Software with Rating Scales. Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal (in review)
- Sooyong Lee, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2023). Comparison

between Bayesian or ML in FLPS with Small Sample Sizes. (in progress) Sooyong Lee, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2023). Multidimensional FLPS. (in progress)

Program

GRshiny: Graded response model

Shiny application 2022

o https://sooyonglee.shinyapps.io/GRShiny/

Embeded Standard Setting Shiny application

2021

o https://sooyonglee.shinyapps.io/ESS test/

maat package R package

2022

o https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/maat/index.html

FLPS package R package

2022

clavaan package R package

2023

Presentation

Kejin Lee; Sooyong Lee; Youngri Lee

Connecticut, US

2018-05-

An Alternative Approach to Discrete-Time Survival Analysis for Meaningful Interpretation

Modern Modeling Methods conference (MMM)

Sooyong Lee; Sehee Hong

New York, USA

Exploration of LCA conditions in Latent Class with Low Proportion

2018-07-01

• International Meeting of the Psychometric Society (IMPS)

Sooyong Lee; Suhwa Han

Maryland, USA

Item selection and trait estimation methods in CAT with item leakage

2020-07-01

O International Meeting of the Psychometric Society (IMPS)

Sooyong Lee; Tiffany A. Whittaker

Comparison of Three Approaches to Class Enumeration in Growth Mixture Modeling when Time Structures of • American Educational Research Association (AERA)

Sooyong Lee; Suhwa Han; Seung W. Choi

Virtual

DIF Detection with Zero-Inflation under the Mixture Modeling Framework

2021-04-01

• American Educational Research Association (AERA)

Fellowship & Awards

William Hays Endowed Fellowship

Fellowship

Benjamin & Dorothy Fruchter Excellence Award

2020-21 Award

2021-22